Mary A. (Mary Augusta) Jordan Papers, 1885-1931
Smith College Archives
Mary A. (Mary Augusta) Jordan Papers
1885-1931
Jordan, Mary A. (Mary Augusta), 1855-1941
RG 42 UUID:00b1e4c5-52e9-4d7a-8952-220852dc55a0
5 boxes (2.25 linear ft.)
Smith College Archives Northampton, MA
Professor of English. Contains biographical information, correspondence, writings photographs, and memorabilia.
Mary Augusta Jordan was born on July 5, 1855 in Ironton, Ohio. She was the daughter of Edward Jordan, who was appointed Solicitor of the United States Treasury by President Lincoln, and Augusta Woodbury Ricker Jordan. Mary was the eldest of four children. Mary was known since childhood for her exceptional intelligence and love of the English language. She was one of Smith College's star English instructors and her passing was greatly mourned by the academic world she left behind with her death on April 14, 1941.
When her father retired from public office and the family moved to Elizabeth, New Jersey, Mary enrolled in Vassar College where she graduated in 1876, Phi Beta Kappa at the age of twenty-one. She continued with her education at Vassar and received her M.A. in 1878. She was first a librarian (1877-1880) and later an English instructor at Vassar until her departure in 1884.
Mary left Vassar in order to teach at the recently founded Smith College at the behest of President Seelye. Known for her independent nature, Mary was soon a well recognized figure in Northampton and on the college campus. She was a much loved and well-respected instructor in Rhetoric and English, and known for her well intended but sharp wit and constructive criticism. Her home was always open for students to gain access to her extensive library or her ready advice. Although she published few articles, she was known as the star of the English Department and quickly ascended to be first the head and later the chairman of the English Department. Smith College awarded her the honorary degree, Doctor of Humane Letters, in 1910.
Her independent nature and love of learning lead her to devote her entire life to teaching. She was briefly engaged to her cousin, David Starr Jordan, but the relationship did not last. She instead spent her life galvanizing her students' love of learning. She spent a great deal of her time away from the school on extended stays in the homes of friends and family. She made her home at Hatfield House while at Smith.
Mary Augusta Jordan retired from Smith in 1921, after thirty-seven years of service. She continued to remain active however, and concerned herself with the affairs of Albertus Magnus College in New Haven, Connecticut, the area which she moved to after retirement. She was a deeply religious person, although nonsectarian, and the affairs of the Roman Catholic school interested her deeply. It was at 42 Lincoln Street in New Haven, Connecticut, near the home of her niece where Mary fell ill. She died soon after on April 14, 1941, at the age of sixty-five. She left behind an extensive legacy at Smith College, and in 1922 after her retirement, was remembered by Smith College in three ways. There is a Smith house, located in the quad, named Jordan in her honor. The English department also named the Mary Augusta Jordan professorship in remembrance of their colleague. The prize, which is now defunct, was a small scholarship for students who excelled in English literature, named the Mary Augusta Jordan Prize.
The Mary Augusta Jordan Papers contain biographical information, correspondence, writings photographs and memorabilia documenting her career at Smith as both student and professor of English Languages and Literature. Of particular interest is a history of the English Department written by Jordan in 1925.
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The papers are open for research according to the regulations of the Smith College Archives without any additional restrictions.
History of the Collection
The Mary A. (Mary Augusta) Jordan Papers were donated over a period of time to the Smith College Archives from a variety of sources.
Additional Information
Related Material
The English Department Records will provide a researcher with additional information about the administration of the department, and specific courses offered over a period of time. Departmental correspondence is also found in the Office of the President. Faculty papers and biographical files may also provide insight into Jordan's relationships with her colleagues. A listing of faculty members is found in the publication called the Annual Circular.
- Biographical Material and Smith College Material (Box 879)
  - Biographical Material-General (Box 879, Folder 1)
  - Biographical Material-Education (Box 879, Folder 2)
  - Biographical Material-Education, Vassar College (Box 879, Folder 3)
  - Biographical Material-Miscellaneous (Box 879, Folder 4)
  - Biographical Material-Obituaries 1941 (Box 879, Folder 5)
  - Smith College Material-Miscellaneous (Box 879, Folder 6)
  - Smith College Material-Hatfield House (Box 879, Folder 7)
  - Smith College Material-Lecture Notes (Box 879, Folder 8)
    (see also Box 883)
  - Smith College Material-Mary A. Jordan Professorship (Box 879, Folder 9)
  - Smith College Material-Recommendations (Box 879, Folder 10)
  - Smith College Material-Retirement, general (Box 879, Folder 11)
  - Smith College Material-Retirement, Tributes (Box 879, Folder 12)
  - Smith College Material-Retirement, A Tribute of 40 Years (Box 879)
- Correspondence A-Pe (Box 880)
  - A-BE, miscellaneous (Box 880, Folder 13)
  - Abbott, Lyman undated (Box 880, Folder 14)
  - Bacon, Josephine Daskam 1904-1921 (Box 880, Folder 15)
  - Bates, Katherine Lee 1895-1915 (Box 880, Folder 16)
  - BI-CA, miscellaneous (Box 880, Folder 17)
  - Booth, Maud B. 1896-1915 (Box 880, Folder 18)
  - Branch, Anna Hempstead 1897-1934 (Box 880, Folder 19)
  - Brearly, Samuel, Jr. 1885-1897, undated (Box 880, Folder 20)
  - Bridges, Robert Seymour 1895-1900 (Box 880, Folder 21)
  - Briggs, Le Baron Russell 1900-1910 (Box 880, Folder 22)
  - Burroughs, John 1887, undated (Box 880, Folder 23)
  - Cable, Eva Stevenson undated (Box 880, Folder 24)
  - CH-CZ, miscellaneous (Box 880, Folder 25)
  - Clark, Marguerite Dixon 1925-1928, undated (Box 880, Folder 26)
  - Clemens, Samuel Langhorne 1889 (Box 880, Folder 27)
  - Cleveland, Rose E. 1899-1904, undated (Box 880, Folder 28)
  - Cravath, Paul D. 1915 (Box 880, Folder 29)
  - Cutler, Anna Alice 1928 (Box 880, Folder 30)
  - D-F, miscellaneous (Box 880, Folder 31)
  - Dickinson, Lavinia 1895-1897 (Box 880, Folder 32)
  - Drennan, M.J. 1890-1898 (Box 880, Folder 33)
  - Dunton, Edith Kellog 1922, undated (Box 880, Folder 34)
  - Edwards, Hilda Blanche 1911-1928 (Box 880, Folder 35)
  - Ellsworth, Helen J.S. undated (Box 880, Folder 36)
  - Ellsworth, William W. 1897 (Box 880, Folder 37)
  - Folger, Henry Clay 1912-1935 (Box 880, Folder 38)
  - Ford, M. Eleanor 1914-1915 (Box 880, Folder 39)
  - Franchot, C. Pascal undated (Box 880, Folder 40)
  - G-HE, miscellaneous (Box 880, Folder 41)
  - Gallen, P.H. undated (Box 880, Folder 42)
  - Gardiner, Harry Norman 1892-1927, undated (Box 880, Folder 43)
  - Garrison, Wendell Phillips 1894-1898 (Box 880, Folder 44)
  - Gaylord, Emma P. 1914, undated (Box 880, Folder 45)
  - Gibson, Emily H. 1885-1888 (Box 880, Folder 46)
  - Gilbert, Simeon 1893 (Box 880, Folder 47)
  - Greet, Ben undated (Box 880, Folder 48)
  - Hadley, Arthur Twining 1897-1900 (Box 880, Folder 49)
  - Harrison, Bertram undated (Box 880, Folder 50)
  - HI-K, miscellaneous (Box 880, Folder 51)
  - Hyde, George P. 1928 (Box 880, Folder 52)
  - James, William 1891, undated (Box 880, Folder 53)
  - Jordan, David Starr 1899, 1913 (Box 880, Folder 54)
  - Kearns, Elsie Herndon 1914, undated (Box 880, Folder 55)
  - L-MA, miscellaneous (Box 880, Folder 56)
  - Lathrop, Clara W. 1899, 1901 (Box 880, Folder 57)
  - Leach, Abby 1900, 1905 (Box 880, Folder 58)
  - Macmechan, Archibald M'Kellar 1897-1900 (Box 880, Folder 59)
  - McNely, Ruth 1913 (Box 880, Folder 60)
  - ME-PE, miscellaneous (Box 880, Folder 61)
  - Meid, Ella undated (Box 880, Folder 62)
  - Meyer, Annie Nathan 1910, undated (Box 880, Folder 63)
  - Peck, Ludella L. 1886, undated (Box 880, Folder 64)
- Correspondence Ph-Z (Box 881)
  - PH-R, miscellaneous (Box 881, Folder 65)
  - Poland, William Carey 1892-1899 (Box 881, Folder 66)
  - Prescott, Henry Lee 1899-1900 (Box 881, Folder 67)
  - Pruyn, Eva Jenison 1910-1915 (Box 881, Folder 68)
  - Rockefeller, John D., Jr. 1916 (Box 881, Folder 69)
  - Rose, Henry T. 1912, undated (Box 881, Folder 70)
  - S-V, miscellaneous (Box 881, Folder 71)
  - Santayana, George 1899, undated (Box 881, Folder 72)
  - Sharp, Martha undated (Box 881, Folder 73)
  - Shaw, Adele Marie 1914, undated (Box 881, Folder 74)
  - Shoop, Max undated (Box 881, Folder 75)
  - Short, Frank Lea 1910-1911 (Box 881, Folder 76)
  - Steinberg, Mary B. 1899-1900, undated (Box 881, Folder 77)
  - Stoddard, F.H. 1885, undated (Box 881, Folder 78)
  - Taylor, James M. 1899-1900 (Box 881, Folder 79)
  - Thomas, M. Carey 1899-1900, undated (Box 881, Folder 80)
  - Thwing, Charles F. undated (Box 881, Folder 81)
  - Tucker, H. St. George 1921 (Box 881, Folder 82)
  - Ventura, L.D. 1885 (Box 881, Folder 83)
  - W-Z, miscellaneous (Box 881, Folder 84)
  - Ward, William Hayes 1912 (Box 881, Folder 85)
  - Watts, Martha Emma 1914, undated (Box 881, Folder 86)
  - Whipple, George N. 1899, 1915, undated (Box 881, Folder 87)
  - Whitney, Margaret F.G. 1900, undated (Box 881, Folder 88)
  - Withington, Robert 1923-1931 (Box 881, Folder 89)
  - Woolley, Mary Emma 1909-1915 (Box 881, Folder 90)
  - Young, Alfred 1908-1910 (Box 881, Folder 91)
  - Young, Starck undated (Box 881, Folder 92)
- Speeches and Writings (Box 881)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 881, Folder 93)
  - "Assets and Liabilities of Present Day English" undated (Box 881, Folder 94)
  - "A Dressy Bookseller" undated (Box 881, Folder 95)
  - "The College for Women" Atlantic Monthly 1892 Oct (Box 881, Folder 96)
  - "Harry Norman Gardiner" Memorial Service 1927 (Box 881, Folder 97)
  - "Higher Education" Association of Intercollegiate Alumnae 1886 Oct 30 (Box 881, Folder 98)
  - "The Higher Education, A Social Necessity for Women" Association of Collegiate Alumnae 1892 Nov 5 (Box 881, Folder 99)
  - "Influential Fallacies About Education" New England Association of Colleges and Preparatory Schools in School Review (Vol 12, No 2) 1904 Feb (Box 881, Folder 100)
  - "L. Clark Seelye" Smith College Monthly 1910 Jun (Box 881, Folder 101)
  - "Life and the Classroom: 37 Years of It" Smith Alumnae Quarterly 1921 Jul (Box 881, Folder 102)
  - "Ludella L. Peck" Smith Alumnae Quarterly and Memorial Service 1913 Feb (Box 881, Folder 103)
  - "Noblesse Oblige" Pamphlet No. 36 of the Massachusetts Association Opposed to the Further Extension of Suffrage to Women 1901 (Box 881, Folder 104)
  - "The President-Elect of Vassar College and His Problems" Vassar Miscellany 1915 Feb 26 (Box 881, Folder 105)
  - Reviews, miscellaneous (Box 881, Folder 106)
  - "The Return of Nature" undated (Box 881, Folder 107)
  - "The Setting of A College Admission Paper in English" School Review undated (Box 881, Folder 108)
  - "Shakespeare and the Presumptions" undated (Box 881, Folder 109)
  - "Smith College" New England Magazine 1887 Jan (Box 881, Folder 110)
  - "The Teaching of English in Smith College from President and Professor Seelye to President and Professor Neilson" [manuscript] 1925 Jun (Box 881, Folder 111)
  - "The Teaching of English in Smith College from President and Professor Seelye to President and Professor Neilson" [typescript] 1925 Jun (Box 881, Folder 112)
  - "Vassar's Jubilee" Smith Alumnae Quarterly 1915 Nov (Box 881, Folder 113)
  - Correct Writing and Speaking by M.A. Jordan. The Women's Home Library (N.Y.: A.S. Barnes and Co.), 1904 (Box 881)
- Photographs and Sketches (Box 882)
  - Portraits, early pre-1890 (Box 882, Folder 114)
  - Portraits after 1890 (Box 882, Folder 115)
  - Portraits-Endeau Portrait c1901 (Box 882, Folder 116)
  - Snapshots undated (Box 882, Folder 117)
  - Hatfield House (Box 882, Folder 118)
  - Teaching class- Katherine McClellan, photographer 1904 (Box 882, Folder 119)
  - Sketches undated (Box 882, Folder 120)
- Oversize Materials (Box OV)
  - Lecture Notes (card file) (Box OV)
  - Diary 1899 Jan-Mar 6 (Box OV)
  - News clippings/Notes on Education and English undated (Box OV)
  - Sketch Notebook (Box OV)
  - Memorabilia Book of European trip (Box OV)
  - Scrapbook-photographs of works of art (Box OV)
  - Small notebooks (3), miscellaneous notes (Box OV)